She has lymph nodes that are all red, so anyone who touches her
bà bị bệnh hạch nó đỏ hết nên ai sờ bà
is afraid for her. It hurts her whole body, and she
cũng sợ cho bà mà Nó đau hết cả người mà
can't sleep all night, just crying. She
cả đêm không ngủ được cứ khóc luôi bà
just lies in bed, and people bring her
chỉ nằm ở giường người ta lấy cơm cho bà
food. She's had it for 4 or 5 years.
ăn bà bị từ 4 5 năm
[Music]
[âm nhạc]
This woman is Vu Thi Yen, 68 years old,
này tiền bà là Vũ Thị Yến bà 68 tuổi bà
living in Bang Dang village, Viet Hung ward,
ở tại thôn bằng Đăng phường Việt Hưng
Ha Long city, Quang Ninh province.
thành phố Hạ Long tỉnh Quảng
She has lymph nodes, sorry, they're in her
bà bị bệnh hạch hạch nó xin lỗi cháu nó
groin, in her neck, in her armpits,
ở trong bẹn ấy mới hạch cổ ở nách thì
these are tiny little bumps like this, and on her neck, look,
những cái mụn ni ti thế này còn ở cổ thì
everyone can see them. She's had it for
đây đây ai cũng nhìn thấy không Bà bị từ
4 or 5 years, the bumps are this big, they're all
4 5 năm này luôn lổi tầy to bằng này nó
red, so anyone who touches her is afraid for her. It's
đỏ hết nên ai sờ bà cũng sợ cho bà mà nó
affecting her. Maybe it's D? It
bị ảnh hưởng Chắc là D chăng thế là nó
hurts so much, she can't lift herself up, she ca
đau tự nhiên không nhấc được trên lên cả
n't sleep all night, she can't walk.
đêm không ngủ được thế là nó không đi
Lifting herself up hurts, and
được Nhấc lên thế này nó cũng đau mà
lifting herself down is also very painful. She hurts
nhấc xuống nó cũng buốt lắm Nó đau hết
all over, she can't lift herself
cả người mà Nó đau nó không nhấc được
up, she just cries. She has to be helped to walk.
lên cứ khóc thôi phải có người dắt đi mà
Walking from here to there hurts so much, she's so
Đi từ đây ra đến kia bà cũng đau lắm bà
embarrassed. She just lies in bed, and people
ngại lắm bà chỉ nằm ở giường người ta
bring her food.  Sitting in the car
lấy cơm cho bà ăn và cũng không ngồi xe
hurts so much I can't get on a motorbike, it's cumbersome.
nó đau không lên được xe máy đi cập kềnh
Anyway, Ms. Yen also shared that you have to
Thôi c Yến cũng có chia sẻ là phải tu
practice and do all good deeds.
tập và làm tất cả các thiện pháp cái thứ
First, repent; second, practice;
nhất là sám hối cái thứ hai là tu tập
third, make offerings according to
Cái thứ ba là cúng dường tùy theo tâm
your heart. But the most important thing is
của mình Nhưng mà quan trọng nhất là tu
practicing. Then, she massages it herself. Wherever it hurts, she
tập về thì bác tự cạo Đau ở đâu Bà cũng
applies oil for two days before and two days
vỗ dầu hai ngày hôm trước và hai ngày
after. She massages it herself. Some patients,
hôm sau Bà tự vỗ lấy thôi Có BN ngày thô
after four days of massaging, can go back to work. Before, it was
mà vỗ bốn ngày đi làm được Ngày ngày xưa
hard, now it's soft, some have shrunk, you can only
thì nó cứng bây giờ nó nhũn ra có cái nó
feel it when you touch it, but it doesn't
teo đi sờ mới thấy còn nhưng mà nó không
hurt at all, not at all.
đau đớn gì cả không hề đau không hề Dức
Before, it was very protruding, it changed
Thì ngày xưa đ nó cứ lồi hẳn ra nó đổi
completely, and now it's this big. Everyone
hẳn đấy mà đấy nó to như thế này ai cũng
says, "How did she do it so quickly?" She said that after a few days, she could go
bảo sao bà nhanh thế BN ngày mà bà đã đi
back to work normally. She finds
được rồi lại đi làm bình thường Bà thấy
that this method is
là chứa bằng phương pháp này thì không
inexpensive, very simple, and
tốn tiền rất đơn giản nhưng mà lại chóng
cures the illness quickly. It only takes a little kerosene and some
khỏi bệnh chỉ có một ít dầu hỏa một tí
cotton, that's all. And people can make
bông thế thôi còn thì ai đấy mà tùy tâm
offerings according to their hearts. She
của mình cúng dường là tùy theo tâm của
still maintains this practice to this day, massaging wherever it hurts,
mình mà đến bây giờ vẫn duy trì đau đâu
even when she's sick.
là bà vỗ đấy Kể cả bà ốm đau bà Đau ở
Wherever she felt pain, she would apply oil, and she found it soothing,
đâu Bà cũng vỗ dầu thì bà thấy nó nó dịu
cooling, and very pleasant. She expressed her
mà nó mát lắm nó dễ chịu bà cũng gửi lời
gratitude first to the Buddha, then to the
tri ân trước là phật Xong rồi đến đại
Sangha, and to Ms. Yen for making
tăng và đến cô Yến vì đã làm cho mọi
everyone healthy and cured. She
người được khỏe khắn và khỏi bệnh thì bà
was very happy, even though she was old, her
rất là phấn khởi dù tuy già nhưng mà
spirit and will never
tinh thần và ý chí không bao giờ già
faded. From the moment she opened her eyes until the
tươi từ lúc mà bắt đầu mở mắt ra cho đến
day she passed away, many people could only dream of
lúc về đấy nhiều người mơ cũng không
such a thing. From that,
được như thế thì từ cái chỗ đấy thì làm
she became even more diligent and strived harder
cho bà lại càng tinh tấn và cố gắng hơn
to repay her gratitude to the Three Jewels, the
để đền ơn và biết ơn đến Tam Bảo cũng
Sangha, and Ms. Yen's merits.
như là đại tăng và công đức của cố Yến
[Music] [
[âm nhạc]
Applause] [Music] [
[Vỗ tay]
m
m